They, too, were fighting for what they believed in.
（平田）こいつらも
信じるもののために戦ったんだ。
（木村）んん…。
Our goals may have differed, but we pray the souls of both armies' soldiers
（沖田十三）目的は
違えども　死力を尽くして戦った→
両軍戦士の魂が　安らぎとともに→
will return in peace to their home planets.
ふるさとへ帰らんことを
ここに願う。
Salute!
（真田）敬礼！
ドーン
（島）
イスカンダルのユリーシャか…。
Yurisha of Iscandar, huh?
When you were shot, I said to myself, "I must return. I must get back to Hoshina."
（百合亜）あのとき
星名が撃たれたのを感じて→
戻らなきゃ…
星名のところに戻らなきゃって。
And then Yurisha...
そしたら　ユリーシャさんが…。
（星名）よかった　戻ってきてくれて。
うん。
I'm glad you came back.
Yeah.
They survived, but they were all sucked outside the ship.
（土岐）助かっても　みんな
船外に吸い出されたんだろうな。→
Ito may have died, but maybe he was right.
結局　死んじまった伊東さんの方が
正しかったのかな。
Don't be stupid.
（榎本）バカ言ってんじゃねぇ！
（土岐）でも→
But it doesn't make sense!
おかしいじゃないすか。
あのイスカンダル人→
I thought that Iscandarian possessed Yuria, but then she shows up looking like Yuki.
百合亜ちゃんに
憑依したと思ったら→
今度は　雪さんそっくりな
姿で現れて。
（榎本）んん…　そりゃあ→
Well, she's an alien. I guess they can do that.
宇宙人だからな　おかしなもんさ。
（薮）ありましたよ！
I found it!
Idiot, not so loud!
（伊東）バカ！　声が大きい。
S-Sorry...
（薮）ご…　ごめんなさい。
（伊東）はぁ…。
（薮）どうすんすか？　これから。
What do we do now?
今　考えてる。
ガタガタガタ…（物音）
I'm thinking!
（薮）ああ～！
うっ！
いいかげんに…　あっ！
Enough...
（薮）ねっ？
See?
（古代進）くっ！
んん…　ぐっ！
ダン！
（森雪）はっ！
（ノラン）ご気分は　いかがですか？
How are you feeling?
えっ？
（ノラン）私は　イスカンダル語に→
My Iscandarian isn't very good, so I put that on you.
堪能ではないので
着けさせていただきました。
ん？　あっ。
（ノラン）自分は→
I'm Banner Holder Norran Ortschett. I'll be looking after you for a while.
しばらく　あなたの
お世話をさせていただく→
ノラン・オシェット伍長です。
ん？　何か？
Something wrong?
あなた　ガミラス人なの？
んん…。
Are you Garmillan?
キィーン…（ハウリング）
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（ハイニ）間もなく　収容所惑星→
We will soon arrive at the prison planet Leptapoda.
レプタポーダの軌道に入る。→
総員　上陸準備にかか～れぇ。
Everyone, prepare for landing.
収容所？
あっ　いえ…→
Prison?
No, you'll be changing ships there.
そこで　迎えの艦に
乗り継いでいただくだけです。
Where are you taking me?
どこへ連れていくつもり？
デスラー総統のもとへ。
待って！
To Lord Desler.
Wait.
ヤマトは　どうなったの？
What happened to the Yamato?
The Terron ship sank.
テロンの艦なら沈みましたよ。
えっ!?
Prison Planet Leptapoda
バン　バン！　バン！（銃声）
（ボーゼン）間もなく
ここに　高貴なお方がやってくる。
Someone of high birth will soon arrive here.
バン　バン！
（ボーゼン）あんたには→
You will take care of her.
そのお世話をしてもらう。
バン！
（２人）はぁ　はぁ　はぁ…。
バン　バン！
You barbarians just waste food.
（ボーゼン）無駄飯食らいの野蛮人め。
Hail to the Empire!
≪（囚人）うわぁ～～!!
（ボーゼン）相手は　イスカンダルの王族だ。
They are Iscandarian royalty.
（エリーサ）
あっ　イスカンダルのお方が？
Someone from Iscandar?
（ボーゼン）
あいにく　作法を心得てるのは→
Unfortunately, you're the only one who knows the proper etiquette.
あんたぐらいだけでな。
Hail to the motherland!
バン！
うっ！→
うわぁ～～!!
≪コン　コン（ノック）
≪コン　コン
What do you expect of one as old as I am?
（ディッツ）
この老いぼれに　何を期待する。
UX01 is berthing... It's linked up. Lowering jetty.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）ＵＸ－０１　接岸。
係留　完了した。→
桟橋を下ろす。
港湾作業班は　準備に入れ。
Port crew, get ready.
（ハイニ）
こりゃまた　機械化兵だらけだ。
Look at all those mechanical soldiers.
（フラーケン）
どこも似たようなもんだ。→
It's the same way everywhere.
We can't even maintain our territory anymore without those tin toys.
今や　ブリキの兵隊なしでは→
領土を維持することすら
ままならん。→
The downside to expansionist policy.
拡大政策のツケってやつさ。
（ハイニ）無敵ガミラスよ　今いずこ！
Where have you gone, invincible Garmillas?
Welcome to Leptapoda!
（ボーゼン）
ようこそ　レプタポーダへ。→
I am Bozen, Warden of Prison Planet 17.
私は　この第十七収容所の所長
ボーゼンです。→
Bring the Iscandarian to the car. This one will see to her.
イスカンダルのお方は
どうぞ　車へ。→
身の回りのお世話は
この者がいたします。
（ハイニ）ありゃあ　ドメル将軍の…。
（フラーケン）ああ。
That's General Domel's...
Yes.
This way.
（エリーサ）どうぞ　こちらへ。
Captain, I take my leave here, as well.
（ノラン）では艦長　自分もここで。
Where are you going?
（ボーゼン）どこへ行く？
（ノラン）自分には　あのお方を→
I've been assigned the mission to return her to her home.
本国まで送り届ける
任務があります。
That's our task.
（ボーゼン）それは　我々の仕事だ！→
No room for second-class citizens.
二等臣民ごときの出る幕ではない。
We are also Garmillans.
俺たちだって　ガミラス人だ。
Silence, you Zaltzi scum!
黙れ　劣等人種が！
うっ！
（２人）あっ！
That bastard...
んのやろう…　あっ。
You are parasites on the Empire! You have no right to call yourselves Garmillans.
帝国に寄生する貴様らに
ガミラスを名乗る資格などない。
くっ…。
What? Don't look at me like that!
なんだ～？　その目は！
Stop!
≪おやめなさい！
あっ。
Iscandar orders you... Fulfill your mission.
イスカンダルが命じます。
あなたの役目を果たしなさい。
へへっ。
ふっ。
My father was a diplomatic officer,
（エリーサ）父が外交官でしたので
子供の頃から→
so I was taught the proper etiquette as a child.
イスカンダルの作法は
教えられました。
Please.
（エリーサ）どうぞ。
It looks good on you.
（エリーサ）お似合いです。
ありがとう。
Thank you.
W-Wait.
あっ　待って。
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい。
（エリーサ）それは？
What is that?
My sister gave this to me.
姉から託されたものです。
To bring salvation to sentient life on all planets.
（スターシャ）あまねく星々
その知的生命体の救済→
That is the way of Iscandar.
それが　イスカンダルの進む道。
あっ。
（スターシャ）そして→
And that is our clan's task.
それが　私たち一族の使命。
（ユリーシャ）はっ！　お姉様…。
Starsha...
（新見）補修に必要な資源を
入手可能な惑星は→
This was the only planet in the surrounding system with the materials we need.
近傍の星系では　ここだけでした。
I've assembled an away team.
（平田）
上陸班は　すでに編制済みです。
うむ。
（真田）その前に→
But first, this is within Garmillan territory.
ここは　ガミラスの制宙圏です。→
It's possible that they recognize its value as well as we do.
我々と同じく
彼らも　利用価値を→
認めている可能性は
否定できません。
うむ…。
古代。
はっ。
Kodai,
I'm ordering you on recon.
お前に　偵察任務を命じる。
あっ…　いや　しかし　自分は
今　ヤマトを離れるわけには…。
But I can't leave the Yamato right now...
（島）
少し　外の空気を吸ってこいよ。
Get some fresh air, okay?
古代進
当該惑星の偵察任務に就きます。
Susumu Kodai will perform recon on the planet's surface.
≪シューン（ドアの音）
（新見）では　私は営倉に戻ります。
I'll return to the brig.
新見君。
（新見）あっ。
Niimi...
The brig isn't where you should be going.
君の戻る場所は
営倉ではないはずだ。
はい。
Yes, sir.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ビィー　ビィー…（警告音）
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）
シーガル発艦に備え　誘導員は→
All guidance crew to their posts, and prepare for Seagull launch.
速やかに　所定の配置に着け。→
Repeat: All guidance crew to their posts, and prepare for Seagull launch.
繰り返す。　シーガル発艦に備え→
誘導員は
速やかに　所定の配置に着け。
古代は　助けたいと思う？
You want to save her, Kodai?
ん？　うわっ！
What are you doing here?
なんで　君がここに？
雪を助けたいと思う？
Do you want to save Yuki?
Sorry, but I'm on a mission now.
悪いが　これから任務なんだ。
I want to save her.
私は助けたい。
降りてくれないか？
Would you get out? I don't have time to talk.
今　君と話してる暇はないんだ。
When will you have time?
暇になるのは　いつ？
だから！
I told you...
（管制員・通信）
シーガル　発艦状況　知らせ。
Seagull, are you ready to launch?
If I knew where she was, I'd save her... Anyway, would you get out?
俺だって　居場所さえ分かれば…。
とにかく降りてくれ。
She is on this planet.
彼女は　いるの　この星に。
えっ？
（管制員・通信）
シーガル　問題発生か？
Seagull, is there a problem?
No.
（通信）問題ない。
（管制員）了解。　ハッチ　オープン。
Roger. Opening hatch.
ん？
Is what you just said true?
さっきの話　本当なのか？
（ユリーシャ）
本当。　ここ…　彼女は　ここにいる。
Yes, here... She is here.
How can you tell?
どうして分かる？
愛してるの。
I love her.
えっ!?
愛してないの？
Don't you love her?
≫はあ？
≪（ユリーシャ）どっちなの？
Well?
I-I...
えっ　俺は…。
ん？
（伊東）
こんな所で　愛の語らいですか。
Is this where we should be discussing love?
お前たち　生きていたのか。
You're still alive?
（伊東）生きてちゃ悪いですか？
いや…。
Is that a problem?
No...
But it's good to see you taking it easy. Even after so many have perished.
それより
お二人とも　いい気なもんですね。
仲間が　大勢　死んだっていうのに。
森さんにコスプレ。
羨ましいもんだ。
Mori's cosplaying, huh? I'm jealous.
No, you probably don't know, but that isn't Mori...
違うんだ。
君たちは　知らないだろうが→
その人は　森君ではなくて…。
I do know. She's an alien, isn't she?
（伊東）分かってますよ。
宇宙人だってんでしょ？→
Operations Officer Mori... Or perhaps Yurisha, of Iscandar.
森船務長…
いや　イスカンダルのユリーシャ。
It's not like that! Well, it is, but...
だから　違うんだ…
あっ　いや　そうなんだが…。
Don't move.
（伊東）おい　動くな！
（薮）ああ～　ちょっと！→
ああ～　ちょっと　ちょっと！
（伊東）こいつ！
You...
（２人）うわぁ～～！
ピシュ！
ボゥン！
バカ！
ごめんなさい！
You idiot!
I'm sorry!
（２人）うわっ！
くそっ！
Damn it!
みんな　つかまれ！
Everyone, grab hold of something!
ドドォーン！
（ボーゼン）本国の監察官だと？
（通信兵・通信）はっ。→
An imperial inspection ship?
Yes, it will arrive shortly.
間もなく　到着するとのことです。
物資の横流しが　発覚したのでは？
Do you think they know what we've been selling on the black market?
くそっ！　やっと　中央に
返り咲けるチャンスだというのに。
Damn it! I finally had a chance to get back to the home planet!
いや…　切り札は　こちらにある。
No, I still have an ace up my sleeve.
おお～　見違えましたな。→
I barely recognize you. You finally look like an Iscandarian princess.
ようやく　イスカンダルの姫らしく
おなりだ。→
あはははっ！
（通信兵・通信）所長。
Warden.
（ボーゼン）なんだ？
（通信兵・通信）巡回パトロール隊が→
What?
A patrol has discovered what appear to be escaped prisoners.
脱走者らしき者を
捕らえたそうです。
I'm busy now...
今は　それどころでは…。
（ボーゼン）なっ！　えっ？
（ボーゼン）ええい　確かめるぞ！
あっ　それぇ～！
We need to investigate! Get going!
えっ？
あっ…。
あの艦は…。
That ship...
Out of the frying pan, into the fire, huh?
（伊東）
一難去って　また一難…　ですか。
（薮）あんたのせいだ…。
（伊東）ん？
Your fault...
（薮）あんたのせいだ。
（伊東）あっ…。
It's your fault.
（薮）あんたのせいだ！
あんたの口車に乗らなきゃ→
It's your fault! If I hadn't listened to you, this never would've happened!
こんなことに…。
薮！　くっ！
Yabu!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（アナウンス）所長より通達！
拘束した　ザルツ人らしき女を→
Message from the Warden! Bring the Zaltzi woman to him at once.
直ちに　こちらへ連行せよ！
Unlocking
くっ！
うわぁ～！
行け～！
おおっ！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　ウウーー！（警報）
なんだ？
What?
ドカン！
ドカン！　ドカン！
うっ！
（ユリーシャ）あっ。
Wait!
待て！　うわっ…。
古代！
Kodai!
ぐわっ！
（薮）ん？
あっ…　逃げろ！
（薮）ううっ！
Run!
≪ドォーン！
（一同）うおぉ～～！
（薮）ひぃ…　ひぃ～！　うぅ…。→
うぅ…　ううっ…。
ふん！
（薮）うぐっ！　うぅ…　ひぃ…。
（囚人・ガミラス語で）
Are you a prisoner?
ピュン！
（薮）あっ！　ん？
（ガミラス語で）
Fight with us!
Freedom will be ours!
（一同）おお～！
ああっ!?　ひぃ　ひひっ…。
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]　緊急事態！　所内で暴動が…。
暴動だと？→
A riot?
そんなバカな。
しかし…。
Impossible...
But...
（ボーゼン）
こ…　これはこれは　監察官殿。
O-Oh hello, Inspector... I'm a bit busy now...
今　ちょ～っと
立て込んでおりまして。
はい？
Huh?
This way.
≪（看守）こちらです。
（ディッツ）お前…。
You...
（メルダ）お迎えに上がりました　提督。
We've come for you, Admiral.
Security, report in!
（通信）警備隊！　状況を報告しろ。
（通信）ダメだ！→
We can't hold them! There are too many...
暴徒の数が多すぎ…　ぐわっ！
ここを出ましょう。
Let's get out of here.
あっ！
くっ！
（ガミロイド兵）部屋ニ戻リナサイ。
ピュンピュン（銃声）
Return to your rooms.
ピュン！
（２人）あっ！
自由を　この手に～！
Freedom will be ours!
I'm sorry!
（ノラン）御免！
うっ！
ピュン！
ぐわっ！
大丈夫ですか？
えっ　ええ…。
Are you okay?
Y-Yes...
はっ！　こ…　この人…。
This one...
（ノラン）ザルツ人…　我が同胞です。
He's a Zaltzi.
My comrade...
（ボーゼン）
くっ！　こんなことで…。　くそっ！
I won't let this stop me.
H-Hey, is anyone there? Open this door!
おい！　誰かいないのか!?
ここを開けろ！
おお～　わしは　ここだ。　うわっ！
I'm right here!
（一同）おらぁ～！
（ボーゼン）ぐえっ…。
Glory to Gatlantis!
えっ？　ひっ　ひぃ…　ひぃ～～！
ピュンピュンピュンピュン…
（一同）うおぉ～！
どこに行くつもりか
聞かせてもらえませんか？
Can you tell me where you're heading, Officer Mori?
森船務長。
雪を助けるの。
To save Yuki.
意味が分かりません。
I don't understand.
死者を弔うのは　宇宙人も一緒か。
So aliens also mourn the dead?
ピシュン
あっ　あぁ…。
こっちも頼む。
Take care of mine.
ピシュン
なあ　森船務長　あんた…。
Hey, Officer Mori, you...
≫ピシュン
あっ…。
伊東！
（兵）うっ　うぅ…。
Ito!
あぁ…。
あっ…。
（伊東）らしくないことは→
I guess acting out of character was a bad idea...
するもんじゃないな…　ははっ…。
Mori...
森…
あんた　イスカンダル人なら…→
If you really are an Iscandarian, would you make me a promise?
約束して…　くれないか？
えっ？
Take the Yamato to Iscandar. Please... Save Earth.
ヤマトを　イスカンダルに…。
頼むよ…　必ず→
地球を…。
うん。
うおぉ～！
うらぁ～！
（囚人）おらぁ～～！
ピュンピュンピュン…
ドォーン！
（一同）うおぉ～～！
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（ガミロイド兵）監察官ノ艦ニ
反乱分子ガ　乗船シテイタモヨウ。
It appears subversive elements were aboard the Inspector's ship.
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（ガミロイド兵）
指揮系統ニ　混乱ガ生ジテイル。
Confusion has occurred along the chain of command.
（ガミロイド兵）ン？
くっ！
ピュンピュンピュンピュン…
雪！
Yuki!
ふっ。　出港用意！
Prepare to launch!
（ハイニ）出港よぉ～い！
雪…　雪…。
ピッピッピッ（操作音）
Yuki... Yuki!
ううっ！　雪！
Yuki!
雪～～～!!
YUKI!
[ｽﾋﾟｰｶ]（ディッツ）全所員に告ぐ。→
Attention all personnel.
I am Ditz, Supreme Commander of Astrofleets.
私は
航宙艦隊総司令　ディッツだ。→
ただいまより　この収容所は
我々の管轄下に入る。
This prison planet is now under our control.
（ディッツ）無駄な抵抗はやめ→
Cease all futile resistance, and surrender.
速やかに　投降するのだ。
雪…。
Yuki...
（ユリーシャ）行き先は分かってる。
あっ。
I know where she is going.
ユリーシャ。
Yurisha!
教えてくれ。
どこだ？　どこなんだ!?
Tell me... Where is she? Where?
彼らの星　ガミラス。
Their planet... To Garmillas.
星が２つ？
この星は　双子星。→
Two planets?
They are twin planets.
あなたたちの向かうべき星。
えっ？
The one you are heading toward.
私たちの星　母なるイスカンダル。
Our planet, Mother Iscandar.
そんな…　バカな…。
No... That's impossible.
Episode 21: Prison Planet 17
Iscandar offers Earth salvation.
Garmillas would destroy it.
The Yamato's destination, Iscandar, is a twin planet of Garmillas.
As they approach it, what path should they take?
Is hope to be found there?
Next time: The Planet That We Head For.
There are 211 days left before humanity is extinct.
昨日から今日にかけて
猛烈な雨が降った島根県西部。
江津市では降り始めからの雨量が
４７０ミリを超えるなど、記録的
な豪雨となった。